Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in the Walt Whitman Collection, Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center at the University of Texas at Austin
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
- Works, 1846-1913 and undated
  - I do not expect to see myself… [I do not expect to see myself], about 1870; tex.00023; xxx.00597; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Lightly revised manuscript fragment of approximately 42 words, written with hanging indentation and expressing a confidence in future popular acceptance. Connection with Whitman's published work is uncertain. Christopher Morley, in his foreword to the auction catalog Manuscripts, Autograph Letters, First Editions and Portraits of Walt Whitman ( 1936 ), writes that he believes that the manuscript "was written... on a piece scissored from left-over stock of the green wrappers and end-papers of the 1855 Leaves." The paper is actually more blue than green, however, and the handwriting is more consistent with a date in the 1870s, a period during which Whitman repeatedly complained about how he was treated by American magazines. This manuscript has been pasted to a backing sheet, and the verso is inaccessible.
  - I do not feel to write… [I do not feel to write], about 1867; tex.00228; xxx.00524; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 5)
    This prose fragment, heavily revised, is almost certainly part of the draft material that contributed to the essay eventually titled Democratic Vistas, published as a pamphlet in 1871. This long essay was originally organized as a series of three shorter pieces, The first two of which were published in The Galaxy, under the titles Democracy ( December 1867 ) and Personalism ( May 1868 ).
  - [I have had serious doubts], about 1891; tex.00094; xxx.01005; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Partial draft, heavily revised, of what appears to have been intended as a preface to a late edition of Leaves of Grass. The manuscript leaf has been pasted to a backing sheet, and the verso is inaccessible.
  - [I have heard spars], about 1872; tex.00024; xxx.00694; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Two lines, with revisions, possibly related to the poem The Mystic Trumpeter, which was first published in the February 1872 issue of The Kansas Magazine. It also appeared in As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free ( 1872 ), Two Rivulets ( 1876 ), and subsequent editions of Leaves of Grass.
  - [I know many beautiful things about men and women], undated; tex.00031; xxx.00695; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Draft of lines that are possibly related to what eventually became section 24 of Song of Myself, a version of which first appeared in the 1855 edition Leaves of Grass. Lines on the reverse are continuous with those on the front—a rarity in Whitman manuscripts.
  - In Western Texas, undated; tex.00101; xxx.00696; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Note, approximately 25 words, about the Texan landscape. No relationship is known between this manuscript and Whitman's published work.
  - Is it enough to keep on importing the first class production… [Is it enough to keep on importing], between 1868 and 1870; tex.00232; xxx.00524; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Prose manuscript fragment, written on a small scrap of paper, apparently from the drafting sessions that produced Democratic Vistas, which was first published at the end of 1870 (though dated 1871 ). Because the scrap is pasted to a backing sheet, no image of the verso is available.
  - It is among these, or some one of these… [It is among these], undated; tex.00090; xxx.00502; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Two small scraps pasted together. On one side is a sentence describing Whitman's visits in Civil War hospitals, probably drafted for Memoranda During the War ( 1875–76 ). On the reverse are three words/fragments of words, which bear an uncertain relationship to Whitman's published writing.
  - Life Life, 1888; tex.00033; xxx.00351; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 1)
    A draft, lightly revised, of the poem Life, which was first published in the New York Herald on April 15, 1888. On the verso appears the handwritten date: June 8. '88.
  - Light and the senses abdicate… [Light & the senses abdicate], probably about 1865; tex.00034; xxx.00697; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 1)
    This manuscript of approximately four heavily revised lines may have contributed to the poem Chanting the Square Deific, first published in Sequel to Drum-Taps ( 1865–66).
  - Make a poem… [Make a poem], probably after 1880; tex.00035; xxx.00698; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Prose fragment suggesting a poem whose "central theme" would be "the Untellable." No relationship is known between this manuscript and Whitman's published work.
  - How I Get Around and Take Notes at Sixty Distant Sounds, about 1881; tex.00226; xxx.00837; xxx.00924; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 5)
    The fourth and fifth leaves of the printer's copy for How I Get Around at 60, and Take Notes. (No. 2.), which was published in the Critic on April 9, 1881. Though he did not include this essay as a whole in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ), Whitman reprinted parts of it under different titles. The first of the sections shown here appeared as Distant Sounds.
  - MY 71st YEAR MY 71st YEAR, 1889; tex.00036; xxx.00384; poetry 1 leaf proof with revisions (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Corrected proof of My 71st Year, which appeared in the November 1889 issue of The Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine.
  - Nevertheless it must be distinctly admitted… [Nevertheless it must], about 1880; tex.00098; xxx.00534; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Notes about Emerson and democracy, probably toward what would become the 1880 essay Emerson's Books, (The Shadows of Them.), which appeared in the May 22, 1880, Boston Literary World. It was reprinted in part in the New York Tribune on May 15, 1882, as A Democratic Criticism. By Walt Whitman. Finally, it appeared in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ). The notes on the other side, tex.00462, probably contributed to the preface Whitman wrote for the 1876 issue of Leaves of Grass and Two Rivulets as a two-volume set.
  - Nevertheless it must be distinctly admitted… [L. of G.], about 1876; tex.00462; xxx.00528; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 3)
    These fragmentary notes were probably written as Whitman drafted the preface for the publication in 1876 of Leaves of Grass and Two Rivulets as a two-volume set. The preface was reprinted in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) under the title Preface, 1876, to L. of G. and 'Two Rivulets,' Centennial Edition. The notes on the reverse side, tex.00098, are probably related to the essay Emerson's Books, (The Shadows of Them.)
  - November Boughs [George Fox], about 1888; tex.00038; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 3)
    This manuscript fragment seems to have functioned partly as reading notes and partly as draft material for the George Fox (and Shakspere) section of Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks. The essay was first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Now Precedent Songs, Farewell Now precedent songs, Farewell, 1888; tex.00092; xxx.00373; poetry 2 leaves handwritten (Box 2, Folder 1)
    A draft of the poem Now Precedent Songs, Farewell, which first appeared in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and was reprinted in the 1891–92 printing of Leaves of Grass.
  - The Mystic Trumpeter [Now, trumpeter], about 1872; tex.00081; xxx.00272; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box bv2)
    Nine draft lines, uncorrected, of section 8 of The Mystic Trumpeter, a poem first published in The Kansas Magazine in February 1872. It was reprinted in As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free ( 1872 ), Two Rivulets ( 1876 ), and subsequent editions of Leaves of Grass. On the verso, someone—perhaps a collector or archivist—jotted a note about From Noon to Starry Night and The Mystic Trumpeter.
  - O I think I could not be the solid land… [O I think I could not be the], between 1861 and 1865; tex.00040; xxx.00177; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Approximately four draft lines, showing a moderate amount of revision, for the poem Song of the Banner at Daybreak, first published in 1865 in Drum-Taps and reprinted, with revisions, in subsequent editions of Leaves of Grass.
  - On, on the Same, ye Jocund Twain, Manuscript On, on the same, ye jocund twain!, about 1891; tex.00071; xxx.00383; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box bv2)
    Heavily revised draft, approximately fourteen lines, of On, on the Same, Ye Jocund Twain!, a poem first published in Good-Bye My Fancy in 1891.
  - On, on the Same, ye Jocund Twain, Proof with handwritten corrections On, on the Same, Ye Jocund Twain!, tex.00080; xxx.00383; poetry 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box bv2)
    Heavily revised proof sheet of On, on the Same, Ye Jocund Twain! The poem first appeared in Good-Bye My Fancy in 1891. This proof has been pasted to another sheet and no verso image is available.
  - …or even scientific values, having done their office… [or even scientific values, having], about 1888; tex.00276; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 3)
    This manuscript fragment is a partial draft of George Fox (and Shakspere.), the final section of Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks, an essay first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Patroling Barnegat Patroling Barnegat, 1880 or 1881; tex.00041; xxx.00140; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Proof sheet with handwritten corrections, apparently prepared for the April 1881 publication of Patroling Barnegat in Harper's Monthly. The poem had been first published in The American in June 1880. It was later reprinted in Leaves of Grass ( 1881–82 and 1891–92 ).
  - Pictures Pictures, between 1850 and 1867; tex.00042; xxx.00159; xxx.00177; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Poetry manuscript titled Pictures, approximately six lines, heavily revised. The first few lines of this manuscript appeared, further revised, in The Runner, first published in the 1867 edition of Leaves of Grass. The middle section of the manuscript is possibly related to Song of the Banner at Daybreak, which was first published in 1865 in Drum-Taps. A different version of last the two lines of the manuscript appear in another poetry draft, also titled Pictures, now in Yale University's Beinecke Library. The writing on the verso is not Whitman's.
  - Poem of the Woods Poem of The Woods, probably between 1860 and 1880; tex.00043; xxx.00700; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Notes toward a poem to be titled either Poem of the Woods or Poem of the Prairies, intended for a "Chicago edition" that never materialized. Any relationship between this manuscript and Whitman's published work is unknown. The notes are written on the back of a page from Sartain's Magazine, which folded in 1852.
  - Poem of Triumph Poem of Triumph, probably between 1860 and 1880; tex.00032; xxx.00701; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Prose notes, draft lines, and trial titles for a poem or perhaps several poems about a triumphant attitude toward approaching death. One of the notes shows that Whitman considered writing a poem that would include a list of what poems are yet wanted. No relationship is known between this manuscript and Whitman's published work.
  - Proud Music of the Sea-Storm Proud music of the Sea-storm, about 1869; tex.00063; xxx.00262; poetry 9 leaves handwritten (Box bv10, Folder 1)
    Printer's copy of Proud Music of the Sea-Storm, published in The Atlantic Monthly in February 1869. In subsequent printings, the title was altered to Proud Music of the Storm.
  - Proud Music of the Sea-Storm Proud Music of the Sea-Storm, 1869; tex.00102; xxx.00262; poetry 1 leaf folio proof (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Folio proof of Proud Music of the Sea-Storm with the handwritten annotation "Atlantic Monthly, February."
  - Good-bye My Fancy: Sail out for Good, Eidólon Yacht Sail out for good, Eidólon yacht, 1890; tex.00067; xxx.00380; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box bv6)
    Heavily revised draft, nine lines, of Sail Out for Good, Eidólon Yacht! which was first published in Lippincott's Magazine in March 1891. It was reprinted in Good-bye My Fancy ( 1891 ). Whitman's note at the bottom calls the manuscript rough crude outlines and dates it July 25 1890. Included with the manuscript is a three-page letter to Alfred, Lord Tennyson, dated 1878, drafted on the reverse sides of letters from Berry Young and Richard M. Bucke.
  - Scintilla Scintillations, tex.00115; xxx.00702; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Draft of several partial lines or trial titles, the relation of which to Whitman's published work is not known.
  - Shakespeare-Bacon's Cipher Shakspere-Bacon's Cipher, undated; tex.00083; xxx.00390; poetry 1 leaf proof with handwritten correction (Box bv2)
    Page proof with handwritten corrections. This poem first appeared as Shakspere Bacon's Cipher in The Cosmopolitan 4 ( October 1887 ): 142. It was reprinted in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ) under the title Shakspere-Bacon's Cipher. An image of the verso is forthcoming.
  - Shakespeare-Bacon's Cipher Shakspere-Bacon's Cipher, undated; tex.00084; xxx.00390; poetry 1 leaf proof with handwritten correction (Box bv2)
    Proofs with handwritten corrections and additions. The poem first appeared as Shakspere Bacon's Cipher in The Cosmopolitan 4 (October 1887): 142. It was reprinted in Good-Bye My Fancy (1891) under the title Shakspere-Bacon's Cipher.
  - Songs for lilac times for 1870-71 Songs for Lilac-times, about 1870; tex.00045; xxx.00703; poetry 1 leaf notes (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Title, note, and verse fragment, approximately twenty-five words, probably related to the poem Warble for Lilac-Time, which was first published in The Galaxy in May 1870. On the verso is a letter drafted in an unknown hand on behalf of the US Attorney General, dated Feb. 12, 1869.
  - Starry Union Starry Union, probably after 1870; tex.00110; xxx.00607; poetry 2 leaves handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Draft lines, heavily revised, for a poem titled Starry Union. Originally a single leaf, the top third has become detached. Starry Union was never published in Whitman's lifetime, though several different draft forms exist.
  - Title suggestions for works, notes Supplement-Sands, about 1884; tex.00111; xxx.00704; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    The words "Supplement-Sands" are written in blue crayon on a scrap of paper, apparently torn from a letter. The verso features the beginning of the letter from an autograph seeker, written in Lisbon, NH, 28 January 1884.
  - Thanks in Old Age [Thanks in old age], about 1887; tex.00074; xxx.00357; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box bv2)
    Heavily revised draft of approximately seven lines of the poem Thanks in Old Age, which was first published on 24 November 1887 in the Philadelphia Press. It was reprinted in the New York World on 23 November 1890 under the title Walt Whitman's Thanksgiving and in the so-called deathbed edition of Leaves of Grass ( 1891–92 ) under its original title. This manuscript has been pasted to a backing sheet and no image of the verso is available.
  - Thanks in Old Age Thanks in Old Age, undated; tex.00087; xxx.00357; poetry 1 leaf proof with handwritten comment (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Proof with handwritten note about publication date by Whitman.
  - The Ballroom was swept and the floor white… [The ball-room was swept], about 1860; tex.00011; xxx.00705; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Three lines of a poem beginning "The ball-room was swept, and the floor white." The relationship between these lines and Whitman's published poetry is unknown. On the verso is a fragment of an apparent letter, which Edwin Haviland Miller dates August 1860, to Thayer and Eldridge, concerning their loan to Henry Clapp of $200.
  - The Dead Tenor The Dead Tenor, 1884; tex.00016; xxx.00348; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Signed draft of The Dead Tenor, approximately 14 lines, written on several scraps pasted together. A newspaper clipping with the death notice of Pasquale Brignoli is pasted in the bottom lefthand corner. The poem was first published on 8 November 1884 in the Critic and reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex of Leaves of Grass ( 1891–92 ). Whitman was inspired to write the poem by the death of Pasquale (or Pasqualino) Brignoli (1824–1884), a tenor who made his New York debut in 1854 and remained a popular favorite for twenty years. According to Horace Traubel, Whitman appears to have known Brignoli. On the verso can be found various writings, including an earlier draft of The Dead Tenor, part of a letter to Whitman from Charles F. Blanch, and an unidentified prose jotting by Whitman.
  - Edgar Poe's Significance Edgar Poe's Significance, 1882; tex.00326; xxx.00931; prose 5 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Printer's copy of an essay published in the June 3, 1882, issue of the Critic and later reprinted in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ) and in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - The epos of democracy… [The Epos of Democracy], about 1865; tex.00019; xxx.00706; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Heavily revised draft of approximately five lines. Connections between this manuscript and Whitman's published work are uncertain, but the lines bear some resemblance to the poem Ashes of Soldiers, first published in Drum-Taps in 1865. This manuscript is pasted down and no verso image is available.
  - Even in the old attack and 6th or 7th recurrence… [even in the old attack], about 1888; tex.00213; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Heavily corrected draft of a phrase that appears at the end of the Prefatory Note section of Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks, an essay first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1891–1892 ). The draft is written on what was apparently a book wrapper. The printed text on the inside of the wrapper is from the Seventh Annual Report of the Dante Society, which was dated May 15, 1888.
  - The following are but casual fragments... [The following are but casual fragments], about 1888; tex.00216; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 5)
    A small scrap on which is written a heavily revised sentence of the Prefatory Note in Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks, an essay first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1891–1892 ).
  - For hospital article… [for Hospital article], probably 1888; tex.00218; xxx.00485; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Notes, written on an opened-up envelope addressed to Whitman and postmarked August 1884, apparently indicating the page numbers of Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) on which appeared anecdotes that Whitman hoped to incorporate into an article about Civil War hospitals. Such an article, which uses some but not all of the anecdotes, appeared under the title Army Hospitals and Cases. Memoranda at the Time, 1863–66 in Century Illustrated Magazine 36 ( October 1888 ), 825–830. When it was revised and reprinted in November Boughs ( 1888 ) as Last of the War Cases: Memorandized at the time, Washington, 1865–'66, the material from Specimen Days & Collect was omitted. This version was also reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Autumn Rivulets: The Prairie States The Prairie States, about 1880; tex.00029; xxx.00260; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Signed manuscript, lightly revised, of the poem The Prairie States, which was first published, in manuscript facsimile, in The Art Autograph in March 1880. It was later printed in the 1881–82 and later printings of Leaves of Grass.
  - To change the book--go over the whole… [To change the], undated; tex.00047; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    This note of approximately fifty words contains Whitman's exhortation to himself to make "the book," presumably Leaves of Grass, "more intensely the poem of Individuality."
  - Sands at Seventy: To Get the Final Lilt of Songs To get the final lilt of songs, about 1888; tex.00086; xxx.00346; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box bv8)
    Manuscript, heavily revised, of To Get the Final Lilt of Songs, which was first published in the April 16, 1888 issue of the New York Herald under the title The Final Lilt of Songs. It was later included, under its final title, in the Sands at Seventy annex to the so-called deathbed edition of Leaves of Grass ( 1891–92 ).
  - To getter up of the books—Printer and proof reader, about 1876; tex.00105; xxx.#####; poetry 2 pages handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Full handwritten instructions by Whitman for the printer and proofreader of the London reprint of Leaves of Grass (1876).
  - To the Man-of-War-Bird To the Man-of-War-Bird, about 1878; tex.00049; xxx.00134; poetry 1 leaf proof with corrections (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Clipping of The Man-of-War-Bird, with handwritten revisions, from the November 16, 1878 Philadelphia Progress. The poem had first appeared in the London Athenaeum, on 1 April 1876. The poem was included in some copies of Leaves of Grass ( 1876 ). In the 1881–82 and later printings of Leaves of Grass it was included in the Sea-Drift cluster. The newspaper clipping has been pasted down and no verso image is available.
  - To the Sunset Breeze, Manuscript early draft ?To the ?sunset Breeze, about 1889; tex.00051; xxx.00394; poetry 2 leaves handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    A heavily revised early draft of To the Sun-set Breeze, a poem first published in Lippincott's Magazine as To the Sunset Breeze, in December 1890. It later appeared in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ) and, as part of the Good-Bye my Fancy annex, in the so-called deathbed edition of Leaves of Grass ( 1891–92 ).
  - To the Sunset Breeze, Manuscript intermediate draft To the sunset breeze, 1889; tex.00053; xxx.00394; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Heavily revised intermediate draft, approximately sixteen lines, of To the Sun-set Breeze, which was published in Lippincott's Magazine as To the Sunset Breeze in December 1890, in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ) and, as part of the Good-Bye my Fancy annex, in the so-called deathbed edition of Leaves of Grass ( 1891–92 ).
  - To the Sunset Breeze, Manuscript late draft To the Sun-Set Breeze, about 1890; tex.00052; xxx.00394; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Printer's copy, sixteen lines, with minor revisions. To the Sun-set Breeze was first published in Lippincott's Magazine as To the Sunset Breeze in December 1890. It later appeared in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ) and, as part of the Good-Bye my Fancy annex, in the so-called deathbed edition of Leaves of Grass ( 1891–92 ).
  - To the Year 1889 To the Year 1889, tex.00050; xxx.00389; poetry 1 leaf proof (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Page proof with handwritten information on the poem's initial publication in the Critic on 5 January 1889. Retitled To the Pending Year, it was included in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ) and, as part of the Good-Bye my Fancy annex, in the so-called deathbed edition of Leaves of Grass ( 1891–92 ).
  - The Tramp and Strike Questions, notes The tramp & strike questions, about 1882; tex.00311; xxx.00539; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)